In this clip I'm going to talk to you about some other accessories that make turning a bowl on a lathe a much more pleasurable experience.
The first thing you might need is a compass.
This compass can draw a circle on a half a log up to three inches in diameter.
So it's not the same kind of compass that you might have used in grade school.
You do have to get this from a wood turning, or wood working specialty store.
It has a carbide chip scribe, which is used to scribe your circle, but I could replace this with a pencil or a pen if I wanted to.
Tape measure.
Always very easy and very handy to have around.
Other measuring devices.
This is a flexible curve ruler.
It's nice to be able to use around areas or curves where a tape measure wouldn't fit.
These are calipers.
The calipers are used to measure the wall thickness of your bowl.
When you turn a bowl, you want to make sure that your wall thickness is uniform all the way through because if, as you're roughing out a bowl and its green wood, if your wall thickness isn't uniform you're going to have cracking and the bowl blank will be useless.